Welcome to this Business Central launch
event session for the 2023 release wave
two.
In this session, we're going to talk
about performance testing before go
live.
How you can do that with the performance
toolkit, aka BCPT.
We have a lot of ground to cover, but
it's not going to be a long session. I
hope it's going to be interesting for
you.
We go through a better world. Let's go
to a different galaxy.
We talk about GoPro lives, how to use
the performance toolkit in DevOps, how
we use envision open sourcing test
suites for for business for BCPT.
The future direction of the tool and the
way it's being used, and then end up
with some learning resources and go dos.
So, imagine
a world in a galaxy quite the distance
away.
In this galaxy,
we have some aliens. We call them
aliens. They don't think of themselves
as aliens. They work with ERP looks,
which is ERP in their language. It's a
very diverse crowd, many different types
of species,
but they have one thing in common,
except they all have these names that
end in ooks.
They work with different parts of ERP in
a partner organization. It's actually a
parallel universe, so we have account
managers, product owners, developers,
operations managers, and product owners.
And I managed to intercept
quotes from these
over the wire, probably through a
wormhole.
For instance, Snulks, Snulks, who is an
account manager,
he said, translated into our language,
"By the way,
I just ran a performance test on the
suggested load from the customer. We're
good."
Nice.
Seems like they're playing golf.
Drolks, who is a product owner in an
ISV,
uh
says,
"Just got an alert on Teams. Seems like
we have a performance regression on
version 42." Hm.
Also have time to ride the bicycle.
Here is Chalks.
She is a developer.
Haha. Concurrent test, concurrency
testing, my code is fun.
Don't think anyone really thinks that
here on Earth.
It breaks It breaks Sulks' code when
running with 15 users.
And maybe she also asked if someone
could take the gears out of her head.
Quolks, who is working in operations,
is quoting or quoted to say, "Business
Central runs slower on customer blues on
upcoming version 256,
rolling out next week. Let's
investigate."
And then finally Xulks, who is working
as a project project manager,
delivering projects,
"Before go live" This is why this is
this is the go live, but all the these
other Hopefully, you can relate to these
other scenarios as well. But before go
live,
the project manager tested that the
system scales with the expected number
of ulksers, which is users in their
language, and what they're supposed to
do in the system." Hm.
What a nice fantastic parallel universe.
But meanwhile, back on Earth,
we actually have a tool that can help
you do this. It's called Business
Central Performance Toolkit, or BCPT.
With Microsoft, we abbreviate
everything.
It's a multi-user benchmarking tool. You
can simulate multiple users running
simultaneously.
You can measure performance, detect
locking issues, and test usage
on a system under load.
But the key thing for this tool is it's
not
um it's not unit tests. These are
scenarios that you define, and you run
scenarios
with multiple users.
So, think about
performance activities in a project for
a customer, or if you're an ISV, exact
same things would apply for an app.
When you plan the projects, you want to
do some kind of simulation on on load on
the system.
When you deploy, or when you test, you
actually want to see if the customer
customizations impact anything.
Maybe you want to first of all test on a
plain vanilla Business Central, then you
want to add some apps, and then see if
that actually change the performance
profile on that system.
Acceptance testing uh is also where this
tool can help you. And then, when you go
into operations,
uh and maintenance, then regressing on
updates, regressing whether it's
Business Central upgrades or app
updates,
um that's also something where it would
be nice to kind of see before you go
update to a a next version of something,
or you install a new app,
uh how is that going to change the
performance on your system for scenarios
for the users, not for specific
operations. This is how how the Business
Central
Performance Tool Toolkit can help.
So, let's talk about Pro Go Live as as I
hope to see this in the future.
Testing performance before go live
should be as simple as 1 2 3.
One, you plan and set up your test.
That's easy for me to say, right?
A project manager will go, "What exactly
do we need?" Let's Let's talk about that
in the next slide.
Second, run the tests. Should be Should
we hire 50 people to type in? No, you
should run the tests using this tool.
And number three is analyze and react.
So, what does that mean?
For planning and setup,
most important thing is here.
Together
with the project sponsor on the customer
side, meaning this is a joint effort, at
least something you should do together
with your customer. You need to identify
which are the key scenarios that just
must work and must work fast. Okay? So,
define scenarios and do that together
with the project sponsor.
The rest is just mechanics.
Copy the production environment to a
sandbox.
Set up telemetry so that you actually
have something to get the data and and
alert and and and and analyze. Talk
about that later.
Get
the scenario codes from GitHub. These
are open source. And
if there are scenarios not covered,
just write that code
and submit maybe back to the open source
community
for for everyone else.
If we do this together,
talk a little bit about that later,
it shouldn't be really hard to get to a
very good coverage of scenarios that
anyone can do, so that performance
testing is not a tax. It's just
something that is easy to do.
All right. Now we need to run things.
There are two different ways you can do
this.
You can either just install and
configure the AL extension to VS Code
and run from the tool.
Or you could consider setting up, if you
use AL Go for GitHub, you could set up
your scenario loads as DevOps pipelines.
This would completely automate your
performance testing. Just run a pipeline
and you're done.
Either or, you run your scenarios with
Business Central Performance Toolkit,
and then you analyze and react. How do
you do that? Well, because you have
enabled telemetry,
you can just install the Power BI app on
telemetry, and you have reports right
there to kind of show you the results.
And if if you are really advanced, or
maybe not really advanced, but after
having done this manually, maybe you
just want to set up alerts on
regressions, especially if you're an
ISV.
It would be nice to to just see uh
remember that
that product owner from the other
galaxy,
they just got um a Teams message if
there was a regression on version 42,
right? Wouldn't you like that as well?
So, how could you automate that? So,
mainly for the ISVs, but also maybe for
some of the VARs,
you could set up
uh the performance toolkit in DevOps.
Because right now,
um
actually in version 22,
it was possible to run BCP TS part of AL
Go.
But um but right now in version 23,
it's just out of the box. You can run
test uh at a test app of scenarios, uh
add it as a workload, and even com-
compare the results to a baseline run,
right?
It's
very simple. You just once you have
defined your scenarios that need to run,
you add a BCP T workload,
and then you see your test results in
the pipeline.
And the compare to baseline, well, if
you if you if you add a baseline file,
you can even see the difference. For
instance,
do we regress on the number of SQL
statements? Of course, the number of the
duration
diff might might change on the
environment you run. If you run with not
so stable
environments, meaning performance-wise,
you might get some variation here.
But the num- the number of SQL
statements is is something that you
definitely can trust if it goes up.
It's because your your code changed and
you introduced new SQL constructs.
So, how could we have a world where
doing all of this, including removing
the friction for coverage of test
scenarios, how could we do this
together?
Well,
in version 23,
the toolkit itself
can source the test codes from GitHub.
So, no need necessarily to bake it in.
In the previous version,
uh Business Central toolkit had the test
code built in and therefore
if if if we from Microsoft added new
scenarios, you needed to to update your
your tool your your tool. Not anymore.
Uh, as of this version, version 23,
Business Central
the toolkit
can just run and and get code directly
from GitHub and it looks like this.
This is VS code. So, you clear the
credentials cache. You start your
Business Central startup setup wizard.
You select which environment you want to
test, whether it's a online or Docker
sandbox.
You log in.
You select the tenant you would like to
test on.
And then, this is important part.
No, next one.
Uh, select where you want your
BCPT project files on disk.
And now comes the magic.
You either take the standard test that
ship with the product or with the with
the tool
or you simply get the latest tests from
GitHub. So, if someone, including
yourself,
contributed to the open source project
and got it accepted there,
it's available for you and it's
available for everyone else.
So, right now
we have 22 scenarios available scenarios
available on GitHub and hopefully many
more to come.
I'm
I'm trying to my very best that we from
Microsoft add many more.
I hope with this that you get inspired
as a partner and add or other partners
add
uh, scenarios to this so that
the the tax will go down, the friction
will go down uh, with with good coverage
instead of 22, maybe 222 or 2,200 like
the different scenarios that that really
cover the application
from partners, hopefully from you.
And uh and that would make the
the coverage part of the tool even
easier.
Then you need to analyze test results.
And this is you can do this with KQL.
You can also uh if you run it with
DevOps have these small reports.
But maybe the easiest is simply to use
Power BI.
So if you have enabled telemetry before
the test run, you have data on a lot of
things. You just use the Power BI app on
telemetry, look at the performance
report, and especially three different
pages.
There's a page directly showing
performance toolkit results. And for
especially where this BCPT
uh the toolkit tool where it really
shines is concurrency testing that you
have concurrent scenarios running. This
is where you
where you kind of flesh out deadlocks
and database lock timeout issues in
code. Uh and and there are pages in in
the Power BI report for these two,
deadlocks
and uh database lock database lock
timeouts.
So under performance, you have the
performance toolkit report that shows
you any test that took a long time,
timings, and so on.
The deadlock uh report under errors show
you
um issues with deadlocks.
And uh with database locks page, you can
see which um which objects uh were hurt
by the
lock timeouts. Was it background or UI?
In this case, it will all be background
because the
Business Central uh performance toolkit
uh runs everything with background
sessions. You can see when locking is a
problem. Probably not for for BC- PT
because that would be when you run the
test or when you run the the suites. And
you even get insights into the AL stack
trace
both top and bottom of this. Who tried
to take the locks and which which part
of the code was was hurt by the lock
timeout.
And then finally
there's a sequel part to it as well. So
not only do you get the AL stack trace
and the AL
view of things, but you also see the
database view of things. You get the
sequel statements and you can now
investigate
further into that.
So
where do where do we want to take this
tool
in the future?
When we kind of
revitalized
Business Central toolkit as like last
year.
We we put some
We we thought of different ingredients
of success. It's not a prioritized list,
but things we wanted to have to happen
to this tool to to make it work for
everyone. And we have these five
different pillars. Remove friction,
change the culture, collaborate with the
community, enroll ambassadors, and have
better readiness material.
Let's take them one by one.
Remove friction. Hopefully with the with
the
open source
capabilities we do now.
With the way we do integration to DevOps
and with the way we kind of pave the way
towards automation is something where
you would hopefully
over time think of this as just part of
your normal go live or your normal
practice.
That
especially once we have or you have
proper automation,
it shouldn't be a big deal to to set up
a test run and get some results and see
whether a change is going to hurt
performance.
Changing the culture.
Um hopefully also with this
presentation, you see that this
performance testing is not just for
people working in what I call the
basement or in with the technical roles.
Hopefully we can change the culture into
that's just a natural way of doing
business. Just like with telemetry is
not something just for troubleshooting,
it's something to see the usage of
things.
Um why not have performance testing as
part of your pre-sales before you
interact with a customer if customer is
asking, "Can Business Central handle
this load?"
Let's find out. Let's test it and uh and
and run a test.
Community is important when we talk
about both open source, but also
evangelizing this. So I hope that you
with me together with me will take this
into your partner practices, do lunch
sessions,
and kind of evangelize, "Look, it's not
difficult. Let's give it a shot. Let's
invest in it."
And for that uh ambassadors around the
world, not only MVPs, but also you out
there. You can help be an ambassador of
this and and help drive this change.
And then finally better readiness
material. I'll show you that on the
resources. We invested in getting
better documentations
uh and uh
defining hopefully defining the personas
and scenarios that you saw in this
presentation.
Let Let me show you that.
First of all, aka.ms/bcpt
is the documentation for the toolkit.
Here you get
um
you first of all
you you get some guidance of the first
question.
Pre-sales.
How do I answer the question, can
Business Central handle a specific load
for a for a prospect customer?
Take a look to see maybe there's
something there for you to
to operationalize this.
Second thing is how do I analyze
Business Central data? How do you set
up?
But here
we actually
documented all the personas you saw in
that parallel universe in the galaxy
example, they are here. They are
documented as personas and the scenarios
are described here directly on docs.
We also added um an FAQ. Everything you
always wanted to know about bcpt, but
you were afraid to ask.
If you want to go specifically into the
telemetry parts, this is this is the URL
for you, bc telemetry.
Down here, analyze telemetry with Power
BI takes you through how to set up and
run
the telemetry part for
for
um tracking performance including
Business Central a performance toolkit.
So,
go do's.
Directly after this session, before you
go to any other launch event,
find your
Business Central performance toolkit
usage scenario. I'm pretty sure that you
your role has a need for bcpt. And then
the second thing is start building bcpt
into your processes. Pick a process,
use bcpt, start small, expand to grow
that culture that performance testing
doesn't have to be hard.
Embrace open source.
If
if
If every part of your organization have
to do this
then it shouldn't be a tax, right? So
what if 3,000 partners out there
contribute a little bit every day? I'm
pretty sure that we together can build a
pretty decent coverage of
BC PT scenarios that cover the main
scenarios for everyone.
And for that, learn a little bit of Git.
The basics of Git is not really hard.
Spend 10 minutes every morning in a week
and you are done. If you are if you are
not like
if you if if Git
and and and GitHub is is not something
that you do every day.
And then come back to the launch event
and watch some other sessions. In
particular
if onboarding was triggered
triggered your interest, of course you
should watch
the what's new in in onboarding creating
customer-centric onboarding experiences.
If you are working primarily with code
as an ISV maybe,
I'm sure that the AL go for GitHub
what's new session is definitely for
you.
And
for Power BI and reporting for
developers, why why did I put this
reference here? Well,
it's because
once you get a little bit of feeling for
the Power BI,
we're actually doing a lot in Power BI
embed for for the next for this release
and going forward. So once you get
familiar with using Power BI as a way to
get insights into the into the business
process of
go live, why not take your experience
of being data driven here into being
data driven with customer projects and
helping them being data driven
on on their business KPIs.
If you want to learn more,
Yammer is always the place for a good
discussion. Also,
if you want to take the smaller Twitter
Twitch, it's X Twitter.
BC all is the AKA link to rule them all.
This is the one that has all the other
references to all other AKA links.
And if you have ideas for things we can
do better or new,
BC ideas is your friend.
Um as always, everything we cover in the
Business Central launch events is also
something we cover later in BC and in
the office hours. So, this BC office
hours URL is where you both find
upcoming office hours as well as
recordings for existing ones.
And with that,
I wish you a very very good launch
event. I hope you get good learning
opportunities, throw some good parties
at your partner practices,
and thank you so much for having me.